{
  "age": 44,
  "aliases": [
    "/state-house/district-16/marc-lande/"
  ],
  "background": "Journalist Certified Nursing Assistant",
  "directory": "content/primary/state-house/district-16",
  "district": 16,
  "dob": "11/14/1973",
  "education": "Guilford College, BA Anthropology Peace and Justice Minor, 1995 Bethesda Chevy Chase High School, Diploma, 1991 Montgomery College, Certified Nursing Assistant, 2010",
  "filename": "marc-lande.md",
  "full-name": "Marc Lande",
  "general-only": false,
  "jurisdiction": "Montgomery County",
  "last-name": "Lande",
  "party": "Democrat",
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "Do you support the findings of the Commission on Innovation and Excellence in Education? Are you committed to funding associated reforms, and if so, how?",
      "answer": "I agree with the Commission recommendations towards low income school districts, pre-K programs, the literacy programs, teacher outreach, career and technical programs.  Much needs to be done in terms of funding.   I would love to see a sales or property tax that will help fund programs.   A top priority of mine is ensuring every family in the state of Maryland has the ability to get their child or children to an early childhood daycare program.   Another priority which I believe I am the only candidate in  Maryland calling for is conflict resolution classes k to 12th grade.  I fault the Kiran's Commission failure to adequately address this issue.",
      "shortname": "Kirwan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Is Maryland’s transportation spending appropriately balanced between roads and transit? Does the state have the resources to meet its transportation needs? With the cancellation of the Red Line and the advent of BaltimoreLink, is the Baltimore region adequately served by transit?",
      "answer": "Dedicated funding in the Metro development is good for Metro. However, much more must be done by the Federal government to terms of funding the Metro system. Washington DC is the nation's capital.  Our federal government should be tackling the major funding issues confronting Metro.",
      "shortname": "Transportation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you support the legalization of recreational marijuana?",
      "answer": "No.",
      "shortname": "Marijuana"
    },
    {
      "question": "At a time when the federal government’s commitment to Chesapeake Bay restoration is questionable, what new steps should Maryland take to protect this resource?",
      "answer": "n/a",
      "shortname": "Chesapeake Bay"
    },
    {
      "question": "What steps should Maryland take to ensure the broadest possible access to affordable health care?",
      "answer": "More has to be done by the federal government to ensure every American get the best, most affordable health care anywhere on this planet.  However, the state of Maryland can help ensure that Marylanders get the best of possible services through increasing taxes.",
      "shortname": "Health Care"
    },
    {
      "question": "What role should the state play in helping Baltimore address violent crime?",
      "answer": "I feel we should lead the country in gun control.  We have the ability to place iPhone technology in every gun in Maryland. I am in favor of this technology to track stolen guns.  We have the ability to place trigger locks  on every gun so that they do not fire in schools. I am in favor of this and leading the country towards more favorable gun control.  We have the ability to require every new gun sale comes with a fingerprint lock.  Every gun in Maryland should be sold with this technology. Furthermore why do we not have conflict resolution classes for every Marylander k-12?  It starts with the children.  Teaching students ways to control their angry can be a means to reducing crime. These solutions will help crime in Baltimore.",
      "shortname": "Crime"
    },
    {
      "question": "How would you characterize Maryland’s business climate? What can the state do to foster the creation of more family-supporting jobs?",
      "answer": "We should have higher research development credits to green and health care industries.  As a state, we should be looking to lead the green evolution.  Even if this means a much higher tax rate for the 1% of the tax bracket,I whole heartedly agreed.  I feel big government focused around green and health technologies and a safer community will attract investment worldwide to this great state.",
      "shortname": "Business Climate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you support the creation of a non-partisan, independent body to draw legislative and congressional district maps after each census?",
      "answer": "I am a 100% against 'Republican' gerrymandering. Yes.",
      "shortname": "Redistricting"
    },
    {
      "question": "Does the Law Enforcement Officers Bill of Rights adequately balance protections for police and the public? Should it be changed, and if so, how?",
      "answer": "I am a firm believer in Black Lives Matter and as I say, Blue Lives Matter (Police Officers). I do not believe that you have to choose a side.   I do not believe that the Law Enforcement Officers Bill of Rights places inadequate protections in police officers hands. I have heard of no cases in the state of Maryland where a police officer was protected unfairly because of this law.  At the same time, I am fearful that a police officer could avoid prosecution because he is simply a police officer.  So we need cameras for every police officer and we need judges who will be lent to the fears confronting African Americans especially when being stopped for traffic violations.  In this country, there have been innocent people shot down by law enforcement.  In general, there are good law abiding citizens and good law abiding cops.  Unfortunately, I detest that many African Americans fear whenever confronted by a police officer.  We must be working towards social political and economic justice (or equality) in the state of Maryland.  On this issue, social justice is of the utmost importance for us to move forward as a state.",
      "shortname": "LEOBR"
    },
    {
      "question": "What strategy would you adopt to address the opioid addiction and overdose crisis?",
      "answer": "I will support a bill to address this crisis.",
      "shortname": "Opioids"
    },
    {
      "question": "What if anything should the state do to address income inequality?",
      "answer": "I feel the 1%in this country have too much wealth and the lowest 5% have it too hard.  We need big government initiatives that alleviate the suffering for the lower and middle classes. But we should not simply throw money at problems.  From conflict resolution classes,  early education daycare, gun control, affordable health care and real environmental regulations, our state can lead this nation to an equitable community.",
      "shortname": "Income inequality"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do the state’s Public Information Act and open meetings laws adequately ensure Marylanders’ ability to exercise oversight of the government?",
      "answer": "I do believe that all open meetings should be open not closed as loopholes have done.  I would listen to legislation towards greater transparency for PIA.  I do believe that solutions for transparency will be hard to find.  Updating computer systems and thus, making PIAs much more affordable, is a solution that is viable for the state of Maryland. I will support legislation regarding greater transparency.",
      "shortname": "Transparency"
    }
  ],
  "race": "state-house",
  "residence": "Chevy Chase",
  "social-fb": "landemarc111",
  "survey-response": true,
  "title": "Marc Lande"
}
